本字幕由 ShinY 深影字幕组 原创翻译制作
深影字幕组论坛地址 http://shinybbs.com
翻译： 如风  粟   校对/后期： 苏三
阿加莎・克里斯汀: 大侦探波罗\N第十三季第5集
《帷幕: 波罗的最后一个案子》
您应该是黑斯廷斯上校吧
Captain Hastings, I presume.
我是黛西・勒特雷尔 很荣幸见到您
Daisy Luttrell. Delighted.
您好
How do you do?
可怜的波罗先生
Poor Monsieur Poirot
他一直非常期待您的到来
He's been so looking forward to your coming.
都激动坏了
He's quite beside himself.
他最近怎么样
How is he?
相信他看到您会好很多的
He'll be much the better for seeing you.
托比 这是黑斯廷斯上校
Ah, Toby! Captain Hastings.
您好
How do you do?
乘三点四十的车来的吧
Came by the 3.40, eh?
我们一时冲动买下的这里
We bought this place in a fit of madness.
这把年纪了还开庄园
Guest house keepers at our age!
话说回来 这世道免不了
Still, needs must these days...
至少我俩里面 我还有点商业头脑
...and at least one of us has a good business head.
是吧托比
Don't I, Toby?
快点 快点
Chop, chop!
送上校去他的房间
Take the captain up to his room.
当然 您也可以先见见波罗先生
Unless, of course, you'd prefer to see Monsieur Poirot first.
是的 我想先去
Yes, I would.
那就先领客人去休息室 然后再安顿行李
Drawing room, Toby. Then see to the cases.
诺顿
Ah, Norton.
在西卡莫槭树的旁 旁边
Pair of n-nesting b-blackcaps
有一对黑 黑顶林莺在筑巢
down by the sycamore.
这位是...
This is...
无良建筑商
Blasted builders!
比尔 这位是黑斯廷斯上校
Bill, this is Captain Hastings.
黑斯廷斯 你好
Hastings, yes.
我是威廉姆・波伊德・卡灵顿爵士
Sir William Boyd Carrington.
看我这暴脾气
Excuse the tantrum.
我正在装修我的旧所 奈顿公馆 你听过吗
Having my old place tarted up. Knatton Hall, y'know?
这些懒货真是踢一脚动一动
Lazy blighters need a good kick up the backside.
所以你就是那个著名的黑斯廷斯
So you're the famous Hastings?
那个小个子的比利时伙计没完没了地念叨着你
The little Belgian chappie never stops talking about you.
- 你女儿也在这里对吧 - 是的
- And we've got your daughter up here as well. - Yes.
漂亮姑娘
Fine girl.
可惜富兰克林成天只知道
Pity Franklin has her slicing up
让她开老鼠和兔子的膛
rats and rabbits all day.
不好意思 我还要打个电话冲他们吼一顿
Excuse me while I give 'em another earful.
请接塔明斯特 7211号
Tadminster 7211.
波罗 有人来看你了
Poirot? There's someone to see you.
黑斯廷斯
Hastings.
黑斯廷斯 最最亲爱的黑斯廷斯
Hastings, my dear, dear, Hastings.
- 波罗 老伙计 - 我的老朋友 老朋友
- Poirot, old chap. - Oh, mon ami, mon ami!
我差点忘了 这位是才华横溢的科尔小姐
But I forget myself. This is the talented Mademoiselle Cole.
黑斯廷斯上校
Captain Hastings.
你真是老当益壮啊 老伙计
You have worn well, mon ami.
霜华满鬓 却还是腰杆笔挺
With the straight back and the grey of the hair.
但是斯人逝去 你还是忘不了啊
But the wound...that is still fresh, huh?
已经是最好的结局了
No man could have wished for better.
最终 她能够死得其所
Still, she died as she would have wanted.
并没有受到漫长的折磨
No long, drawn-out suffering.
是啊
Bon.
你呢 你怎么样
And how are you?
我? 我糟透了 不 是半截入土了
Me? I am a wreck. No, a ruin.
我没法下地走路 腿跛了也扭曲了
I cannot walk. I am crippled and twisted.
需要像小孩一样被人照料
I have to be attended to like a baby.
但是内在的我 黑斯廷斯 还是健全的
But the core, Hastings, that is still sound.
你是世上最好心的人 波罗
You have the best heart in the world, Poirot.
心倒是不怎么样 但头脑还是一样敏锐
The heart, no, but the brain-as magnificent as ever.
黑斯廷斯 快停下 停
Hastings, do stop, do!
- 这不是在推独轮车 - 抱歉 老伙计
- It is not a wheelbarrow. - Sorry, old chap.
时隔这么多年后再回来 感觉怎么样
So is it good to be back after all these years?
食物实在是太可怕了
The food, it is disgusting.
应该是定量配给吧
Rationing, I suppose.
不 我说的是英国菜
No, it is the English cooking.
还有水 永远是半温不烫的
And the water, always so tepid,
毛巾薄的 简直没法用
and the towels so thin they're of no use at all.
那你为什么回来
Then why did you come?
因为我在报纸上看到了那起广告
Because when I see the advertisement in the newspaper
知道了你的女儿会来这里
and discover your daughter, she will be here...
我突然有了个计划
I conceive of a plan.
我会说服我的老朋友黑斯廷斯过来
I will persuade my old friend Hastings
然后我们会像家人那样团聚
to join us and we shall all be together en famille.
真叫人开心 是吧
It is most agreeable, n'est-ce pas?
你是不是暗中有什么把戏
You're up to something, aren't you?
是的
Oui.
我就知道
I knew it!
要不然为什么来这里
Otherwise why come back to
我们第一次一起破案的地方
the scene of our first murder?
因为 我的朋友 我担心
Because, mon ami, I fear...
这儿很快会再有一次谋杀案
...it will soon be the scene of another.
你确定吗
Are you sure about this?
你觉得我得了脑组织软化症吗
You think I have the softening of the brain?
不 我不是这个意思 但不太可能啊
No. No, but it seems so unlikely -
这么多年之后 在同一地点再次发生谋杀案
another murder all these years later, under the same roof.
没错 就是这么回事
Tres bien, that is how it is.
- 你能制止吗 - 你觉得我该怎么做
- Can't you stop it? - How do you propose that I do that?
你可以警告一下受害者
You could warn the victim.
我不知道谁是受害者
I do not know who is the victim.
那你一定知道谁是凶手
You must know who the killer is.
不知道
Non.
那你到底是怎么知道会有谋杀案的
Then how on earth do you know it's going to happen?
- 我不能说 - 为什么
- I cannot say. - Why not?
因为...
Because...
你还是以前的老样子 黑斯廷斯
you are still the same old Hastings.
你的脸上一点都藏不住事儿
You have the speaking countenance
我可不想你盯着所有的宾客看个不停
and I do not wish you to stare at all the guests
完全管不住自己的嘴
with your mouth wide open and give,
然后 用你的话说 露了马脚
as you say, the game away.
波罗 这话可说的重了啊
I say, Poirot, that's a bit strong.
你知道我还是会打扑克的
I do play poker, you know.
是啊 总是输
Yes, and always lose.
但这可不是游戏 朋友 千万不能犯错
But this is not a game, mon ami, make no mistake.
这次我们可是有任务的
There is here work to be done...
这才是我叫你来的原因
and that is why I ask you here.
你就把动脑的事儿留给我
Now, the thinking you will leave to me,
但是我需要你 我最重要的黑斯廷斯
but I need you, my most invaluable Hastings,
来当我的眼睛和耳朵 去到我去不了的地方
to be my eyes and my ears, to go to places where I cannot go...
去捕捉谈话中的只言片语
...to sniff out the snatched conversation,
和不为人知的秘密 然后回来汇报给我
the shared confidence, and report back to me.
因为我们之间潜藏着一个杀人凶手
For I tell you there is here amongst us a murderer,
而我们必须制止这个人
and that person must be stopped.
这位是柯蒂斯 我的贴身男仆
Here is Curtis, mon valet.
你的贴身男仆 乔治呢
Your valet! Where's George?
他回伊斯特布恩去侍候病重的老父亲了
It was necessary for him to go to Eastbourne to care for his ailing father.
我来了
Well... I got here.
真不简单
Very clever of you.
- 你记得我父亲吧 - 你好
- You remember my father? - Hello.
我听说你给我女儿分配了不少工作啊
I hear you work my daughter very hard,
富兰克林医师
Dr Franklin.
没有的事
Nonsense.
我总是太全神贯注于一件事情了
I'm afraid I get so awfully wrapped up in a thing.
赫尔克里叔叔还好吗
How did you find Uncle Hercule?
不好 一点都不好
Not well. Not well at all.
我答应了芭芭拉要去为她读会儿书
I promised I'd read to Barbara.
我得去...
I'd better...
好像她自己不会读似的
As if she couldn't read herself.
富兰克林夫人怎么样
How is Mrs Franklin?
老样子 变本加历了
The same and rather more so.
她只是喜欢大惊小怪
She just likes making a fuss.
- 这话说的有点过了啊 - 是真的
- That's rather harsh. - It's true.
她完全不在意约翰的工作
She takes no interest in John's work,
没完没了地唠叨她的身体
goes on and on about her health.
你们在这儿呢
Ah, there you are.
以为科学怪人又拖你去他的实验室了
Thought Frankenstein had dragged you off to his lab again.
这是我父亲
This is my father.
- 阿勒顿 - 黑斯廷斯
- Allerton. - Hastings.
久仰大名
Heard a lot about you.
波罗忠实的副官 对吧
Poirot's loyal lieutenant, eh?
你能来真是太好了
I'm so glad you're here.
赫尔克里叔叔总能让你不再自怨自艾
Uncle Hercule always manages to bring you out of yourself.
他一直情绪低落
He gets so sad.
你得让他低落一阵子 亲爱的
Ah, well, you must allow him that, mon cher.
纠结于过去又有什么用呢
What's the use of dwelling on the past?
我们必须着眼未来
We must all look forward.
你整晚看起来都怪怪的
You know, you've been rather queer all evening.
- 我没有啊 - 你盯着大家看来看去
- I don't know what you mean. - Staring at everyone.
完全藏不住事儿
You're so transparent.
可能是因为故地重游 想起了过去和逝者
Maybe it's being back here with its memories and ghosts.
- 这里有过一次谋杀案是吧 - 对
- There was a murder, wasn't there? - Oui.
这房子的女主人被毒死了
The lady of the house, she was poisoned.
她控制了 用你们的话说 家里的经济大权
She controlled, as you say, the purse strings,
但是她的继子女们觉得
but her stepchildren felt
他们没有了生活的自主权
they had no life of their own.
那真是太自私了
That's so selfish.
老人和病人不该倚仗自己弱势
Old people, sick people, shouldn't be allowed
就毁掉别人的生活
to ruin the lives of others.
- 朱蒂丝 - 我没那个意思...
- Judith! - Oh, I didn't mean...
自私可不是老年人的专利
Selfishness is not the monopoly of the old,
这点我能保证 亲爱的
I can assure you, mon cher.
我只是想到了件案子
It's just that I was thinking of this case
有这么一个不像话的父亲 虐待自己的女儿们
of a man who treated his daughters appallingly.
他的长女 算是解开枷锁
But when the eldest steeled herself to... cut the knot, so to speak,
让她的妹妹们重获自由
in order that her sisters might go free,
然后她去投案自首 被判了绞刑
she gave herself up and was hanged.
玛格丽特・利奇菲尔德
Margaret Litchfield.
是的 你怎么知道
Yes. How did you know?
这是轰动一时的案子
Oh... It is a case most famous.
我觉得她非常勇敢
Well, I think she was very brave.
那富兰克林医师 他怎么觉得
And Dr Franklin, what does he think?
他觉得那个老人是自作自受
He thinks it served the old man right.
有些人被谋杀纯属是自找的
Some people just ask to be murdered.
谋杀从来就不是正义的 朱蒂丝
Murder is never justified, Judith.
但在这么一个极端情况下...
But when a situation is so extreme...
这些想法都是谁灌输给你的
Who has been putting into your head these ideas?
- 没有谁 - 一派胡言
- Nobody. - Pernicious nonsense!
其实我过来是为了给富兰克林夫人捎个口信
Actually, I came over to give you a message from Mrs Franklin.
她邀你去她房间
She's invited you to her room.
失陪了
Excuse me.
我就没懂过那姑娘
I've never understood that girl.
她活出了自我 是个好姑娘 黑斯廷斯
Oh, she is her own woman, and a good one too, Hastings.
但是她现在变得如此冷血
But she's become so cold-hearted.
我觉得责任在她身边的人
I put it down to the company she keeps -
那个可鄙的富兰克林医师
that wretched Dr Franklin.
还有阿勒顿 我不喜欢那个人
And Allerton. I don't like that man.
这就是你们所谓的纨绔子弟 是吧
What you call the nasty bit of goods, eh?
- 但是很招姑娘们喜欢 - 向来如此
- But most attractive to the ladies. - Isn't that always the way?
您能来真是太好了 黑斯廷斯上校
I'm delighted you're here, Captain Hastings.
波罗先生一定高兴坏了
Dear Monsieur Poirot must be so pleased.
还是宝刀未老啊 波罗
Sharp as a knife, old Poirot,
虽然他的身体已经不堪一击了
even though he is falling to bits.
对朱蒂丝来说也是件大好事
And it will be so nice for Judith.
这孩子干活太拼了
The child has been working far too hard.
她看起来气色不错啊
She looks very well on it.
我真是太羡慕她了
Oh, how I envy her.
疾病于我如同跗骨之蛆啊
Ill health has been the bane of my life.
枕头 克拉文
Pillows, Craven.
我丈夫特别擅长奴役别人 是吧约翰
Yes, my husband's a real slave driver. Aren't you, John?
你刚说什么 芭芭拉
Mm? What's that, Barbara?
她刚才说你成天使唤可怜的朱蒂丝
She was just saying how you work poor Judith into the ground.
朱蒂丝 是啊
Judith, yes.
我们还有些事情需要... 抱歉
There was something we had to... Do excuse me.
我觉得自己真是不中用
Oh, I feel so inadequate.
我知道自己应该更关心一点
I know I ought to take more interest.
你不该自寻烦恼 芭布斯
You shouldn't worry yourself, Babs.
但是我觉得这太恶心了
But I find it all so nasty,
白老鼠啊兔子啊之类的
the guinea pigs and the rats and everything.
直叫我反胃
It makes me feel quite sick.
我只愿想着可爱的叫人开心的东西
I just want to think about lovely, happy things.
我和芭布斯是青梅竹马 虽然她小了我十五岁
Babs and I are old playmates, even though she's 15 years younger.
比尔亲爱的
Darling Bill.
然后等我从缅甸回来的时候
Then when I came back from Burma
她已经出落成婷婷少女了
to find her a beautiful young lady.
我们家之前住在这附近
My family used to live in this part of the world
比尔会不时来奈顿公馆他叔叔家住
and Bill would come to stay with his uncle at Knatton Hall.
死气沉沉的地方
A mausoleum of a place.
需要女主人的打理
Needs a woman's hand.
我不介意说给你听 当时我的心完全沦陷了
I don't mind telling you I completely lost my heart,
但是她离我而去 嫁给了富兰克林
but she went and married Franklin.
这人完全不懂她
The fellow doesn't understand her.
他只在意他的那些试管 蠢货
He's only interested in his test tubes, damned fool!
来打局牌吧
Fancy a rubber?
该出红心 你个傻瓜
Hearts, you stupid man!
这没得打了 我们得重新开局
Oh, there's nothing for it, we'll have to start again.
我不知道自己是怎么了 整个人七上八下的
I don't know what's got into me. I'm all at sixes and sevens.
我们还没切牌呢
We haven't cut yet!
抱歉 亲爱的 太对不起了
Oh, I'm sorry, dear. I'm so sorry.
这真是太过 过分了
Well, that was pretty g-ghastly.
看他被这么欺负 我实在是忍不下去了
It gets my back up to see him b-bullied like that.
小声点
Keep it down.
但这太 太恶劣了 真的太恶劣了
But it's too b-bad, it really is.
更糟的是 他还忍 忍气吞声
And what's worse, he just t-takes it.
不过就算想反抗 他也无能为力
Couldn't assert himself if he tried.
我们是不是该关上门
Oughtn't we to shut that?
好像还有人在外面
Ah, I d-don't think everybody's in yet.
谁还在外面
Who's still out?
应该是你女 女儿 还有阿勒顿
Your d-daughter, I think, and Allerton.
- 还没睡啊 老伙计 - 我睡不着
- Still about, old chap? - I couldn't sleep.
我想找波罗拿点药
I was going to get some pills from Poirot.
我来给你
Oh. I'll fix you up.
不用去吵醒他
No need to wake him.
你经常这么晚睡吗
Do you normally stay up this late?
外面有快乐的事情时 我可不会早睡
I never go to bed when there's sport abroad.
这种月光下的良宵不应该被虚度
These moonlit evenings aren't made to be wasted.
这种药的药效很强
This is the real stuff.
它会让你睡得像根木头一样
It'll make you sleep like a log.
"安眠" 这药危险吗
Slumberyl. Is it dangerous?
过量的话才会 这是一种巴比妥类药物
It is if you take too much of it. It's one of the barbiturates.
开这种药不需要处方吗
Don't you need a prescription?
确实需要 但我有门路
Damned right, but I've got a pull in that line.
是我的一个老朋友给我介绍的
An old friend of mine gave me a few useful introductions.
很不幸他已经去世了 那家伙叫埃瑟林顿
Dead now, sadly. Chap called Etherington.
莱昂纳多・埃瑟林顿
Leonard Etherington?
就是他
That's the one.
他的妻子 谁能想到她有那个东西
That wife of his. Who'd have thought she'd have it in her?
- 砒霜 对吗 - 对 你也认识他吧
- Arsenic, wasn't it? - Yes. Knew him too, did you?
不 我在报纸上看到的
No, I read about it.
这样啊
I see.
他很风趣 虽然谈不上品行端正
Funny chap, but good company...
但有时候也算谈得来
in small doses.
睡个好觉
Sleep well.
这是卡拉巴豆 又叫做毒扁豆
This is the Calabar bean. Physostigma venenosum.
我最近在用它里面提取出来的
I've been experimenting with various
各种生物碱做实验
alkaloids derived from it.
话说 波罗 这种东西真的更合你的胃口
You know, Poirot, this stuff's really more up your street than mine.
为什么 我的朋友
How is that, mon ami?
因为它还叫做"考验豆"
Well, you see, it's also called the ordeal bean,
可以被用来证明是否清白
supposed to prove innocence or guilt.
你不喜欢老鼠吗 父亲
Don't you like rats, father?
我肯定不喜欢阿勒顿
I certainly don't like Allerton.
原来是这样
So that's it.
我想你也不会喜欢他吧
And I suspect you don't either.
我为什么不能喜欢他
Why shouldn't I like him?
他不是你喜欢的类型
He's not your type.
那我喜欢什么类型
And what is my type?
你根本不知道 是吧
You have no idea, have you?
实际上 我觉得他很有趣
Well, as it happens, I find him most amusing.
确实有趣
Amusing, yes.
并且很迷人 任何女人都会喜欢他
And very attractive. Any woman would.
- 问题就出在这里 - 别闹了 父亲
- That's the trouble. - Really, father!
你昨晚和他在外面呆到很晚
You were out with him very late last night.
- 这和你有什么关系 - 这真是有趣
- What has that to do with you? - This is most interesting.
如果真能这么轻易地检验出
I would find it a great help
有罪或者无辜 我就轻松多了
if I could test so easily the guilt or innocence.
不过之后的问题就是
Then you have to ask,
究竟怎么才算有罪或无辜呢
what is guilt or innocence?
要我说这很明显
Pretty obvious, I'd say.
要杀人的话就会感觉到自己有罪
One would always feel guilt when it comes to murder.
你这么认为吗 外面有很多人我都想杀掉
You think so? There are lots of people I'd like to kill
而我的良心不会受到什么谴责
without my conscience being too much troubled.
我不喜欢小题大做
I do so hate making a fuss.
我有时候觉得
I sometimes think...
如果一个人病了 就应该安静地离去
if one isn't healthy, one should be quietly put away.
天呐 这样可不好 夫人
God, no, madame.
瞧瞧我 腿都跛了
Look at me, all cramped and twisted,
动也动不了
not able to move,
但我却没想过放弃生命
yet I do not think of quitting.
我仍尽力享受生活
I enjoy still what I can.
但你只需要考虑自己
But you have only yourself to consider.
而我还有可怜的约翰呢
In my case, there's poor John.
我觉得自己就像拖累他的包袱
I feel such a millstone round his neck.
但我肯定他从没这么说过
But I'm sure he's never said such a thing.
这些科学家有时会非常沉迷于他们的工作
These scientist chaps can get quite obsessive about their work.
完全正确 有时候 波罗先生
Absolutely. Sometimes, Monsieur Poirot,
我觉得我能听见那些可怜的小生物
I think I can hear the poor little creatures
在夜晚的尖叫声
screaming in the night.
真是很可怕
Perfectly horrid.
斯蒂文和我在这件事情上意见一致
Stephen and I are as one on this.
我有时会非常沮丧
I can get so terribly depressed
甚至会想 如果能够结束这一切才真是解脱
that I think what a relief it would be to end it all.
得了吧 女士
Oh, come, madame.
但是我对别人有什么用呢
But what use am I to anybody?
踏进神秘的未知之地
Oh, to step into the Great Unknown -
然后约翰就会自由了
and then John would be free.
我去帮你拿麦芽牛奶
I'll fetch your malted milk.
我和你一起走 黑斯廷斯
I will come with you. Hastings!
夫人先生 再会
Madame, monsieur.
你还好吗 老兄
All right, old chap?
是的 我需要休息一下
Yes, I need to rest.
我想你在一战时来过这里
I gather you were here in the first war.
是的 在1916年 我来这里修养
Yes, in 1916. I came here to convalesce.
我就是在那时遇见的波罗
That's when I met Poirot.
- 是不是有位老妇人被谋杀了 - 是的
- Didn't an old lady get murdered? - Oui.
我曾经在一个家庭里服侍
I was once in a house
那里有过一件谋杀案
where there was a murder.
她也是一位老妇人 我的一个病人
She was an old lady too - one of my patients.
那个案件不会就是关于夏尔普小姐的吧
It was not by any chance the case of Miss Sharples, was it?
实际上 是的
Yes, it was, actually.
她的侄子弗雷达・克莱被控诉对她下毒
Her niece Freda Clay was accused of her poisoning
但是证据不足 无法起诉
but there was evidence insufficient to prosecute.
你是怎么知道的
How did you know?
我的工作就是要知道这些事情 克拉文护士
Oh, it is my job to know, Nurse Craven.
他总是能明察秋毫
He doesn't miss a trick.
该死的鸽子 它们会造成许多损害
Blasted pigeons. They do a lot of damage, you know.
托比一直是个好射手
Toby's always been a fine shot.
我曾经是的
Oh... I used to be.
我过去在印度时
You know, I often used to think of evenings
常常想象这样的黄昏
like this back in India,
但事实和想象的差别很大
but nothing's ever quite as you picture it.
不知道为什么 我忽然很渴
I don't know why, but I've got quite a thirst on.
我请你们喝一杯吧 怎么样
Oh. Why don't you have a drink on the house? What d'you say?
好主意
Splendid idea!
- 你去过热带吗 诺顿 - 没 没有
- Have you done the tropics, Norton? - No. No, er...
我 我们...我母亲不让我离开
W-W... My hands were t-tied with mother.
你还好吗 伙计
You all right, old chap?
我受 受不了 了血
Can't s-s-st-stand b-blood.
你会习惯的
You'll get used to it.
没什么比猎获几只鸟
Nothing like bagging a few birds
打几只兔子更有趣了 是吧 黑斯廷斯
and blasting the odd bunny, eh, Hastings?
真是有意思
Darn good fun.
你到底在做什么 托比
What on earth are you doing, Toby?
我只是想给朋友们喝一杯
I just thought I'd give the fellows a snifter.
你不能这么做
You'll do no such thing!
- 把那个瓶子给我 - 黛西
- Give that bottle to me! - Daisy...
如果你再请别人喝酒
How do you think we'll ever
这生意我们还怎么做下去
make this place pay if you keep standing people drinks?
他们只是老朋友 黛西
They're old friends, Daisy.
锁起来 就应该这么做
Locked up! That's the way of it.
我不能容许这样
I won't have it.
你不容许 你是谁啊 我倒是想知道
You won't? Who are you, I'd like to know?
我 我非常抱歉 伙计们
I'm... I'm awfully sorry, you chaps.
我们...
We...
威士忌好像喝完了
We seem to have run out of whisky.
反正我也没有那么渴
Do you know, I'm not that thirsty, anyway.
我们马上就要用晚餐了
We'll soon be having dinner.
晚餐 是的
Oh, dinner, yes.
别担心 托比老兄 我们没事的
Don't worry, Toby, old chap. We'll live.
好了 先活动活动腿脚
Right. Stretch the old pins before mess call.
- 他这家伙挺棒 对吗 - 对
- Splendid chap, isn't he? - Yes.
不管他做什么 总是很成功
Whatever he turns his hand to, always makes a success of it.
有的人总是非常幸运
Some chaps have all the luck.
他现在就少一个妻子了
All he needs now is a wife.
只要她不欺负他就行
So long as she doesn't b-bully him.
他不会被欺负的
He won't get bullied.
他不会允许自己被欺负
He wouldn't let himself.
- 那有只该死的兔子 - 有吗
- There's a damned rabbit! - Is there?
在那里咬树皮 我早该把这个地方圈起来
Nibbling at the bark. I thought I'd wired the place.
我的天啊
My God!
去叫富兰克林
Get Franklin!
没事的 勒特雷尔夫人
It's all right, Mrs Luttrell.
没事的 没事
It's all right. That's it.
会好的
It's fine.
富兰克林正在给黛西治疗 她会没事的
Franklin's seeing Daisy. She's going to be fine.
你认为他是故意的吗
Do you think he did it on purpose?
我曾这么想过 但看到他们在一起之后
Well, I did until I saw them together.
我现在不确定了
Now I'm not so sure.
可怜的老勒特雷尔
Poor old Luttrell.
我想黛西是个好人 但一个人是有极限的
I mean Daisy's a good sort, I suppose, but a chap can only take so much.
打完桥牌之后 诺顿多了几句嘴
After the bridge, Norton actually said as much.
我确定勒特雷尔都听到了
I'm sure Luttrell heard every word.
凶手在这里 我就知道
The killer is here! I know it!
- 你怎么知道 - 我就是知道
- How do you know? - I know!
勒特雷尔冲着他的妻子开枪
Whether Luttrell shot his wife by accident
是意外还是故意的 这个很难证明
or whether he meant to...it is impossible to prove.
你能够证明
Oh, you'll prove it all right.
你总是可以
You always do.
如果人生有这么简单就好了
If only life were that simple.
波罗总是能抓到凶手
Poirot always gets his man.
或许这一次他不想这么做
Perhaps this time he does not wish to.
你把我弄糊涂了 老兄
You've lost me there, old chap.
除非是
Unless, of course...
有人躲在灌木丛中
..someone was hiding in the bushes,
就在上校开火的同时 他也开火了
and at the exact moment the colonel fired, they fired too.
那个藏在灌木丛中的神秘杀手
And who might be this mystery killer
会是谁呢 黑斯廷斯
in the bushes, Hastings?
我觉得是那个吸毒成瘾的罗萨里奥・阿勒顿
I wouldn't put it past that drug-addled Lothario Allerton.
吸毒成瘾
Drug-addled?
他曾是莱昂纳多・埃瑟林顿的密友
He was a chum of Leonard Etherington.
那个被妻子毒死的瘾君子
That addict who was poisoned by his wife.
- 你怎么知道的 - 他告诉我的
- How do you know this? - He told me.
你就没想过要告诉我吗
And you did not think to tell it to me?
黑斯廷斯 你的问题就在于
The trouble with you, Hastings,
你太懒了 精神上太懒了
is that you are lazy - mentally.
听着 波罗 我知道我不是个聪明人
Listen, Poirot. Look, I know I'm not much of a fellow
但你也没必要揭我的伤疤
but there's no need to rub it in.
你不喜欢用脑子来工作
You do not like to work with this.
或许你应该让别人帮忙 比如波伊德・卡灵顿
Perhaps you should get someone else on board. Boyd Carrington.
- 当然不行 - 他比我可聪明多了
- Certainly not. - He's a good deal cleverer than me.
那倒是不难
That would not be difficult.
但是波伊德・卡灵顿...
But Boyd Carrington...
是个爱炫耀的讨厌鬼 他的记忆力太差了
Is a pompous bore, whose memory is so bad
他会把你讲给他的故事再讲给你听
that he tells back to you the story that you have told to him!
我禁止你向任何人说起这件事情
Now, I forbid you to speak of this matter to anyone.
- 你明白吗 - 是的
- Do you understand? - Yes.
我只能靠你跟着别人去我去不了的地方
It is up to you to follow people where I cannot go,
跟他们谈话 打探他们 监视他们
to talk to them, to listen to them, to spy on them,
通过钥匙孔偷看
watch through keyholes.
我不会通过钥匙孔偷看
I will not look through keyholes.
好吧 好吧 你不用通过钥匙孔偷看
Oh, very well, very well, you will not look through keyholes.
你继续做你的英国绅士 然后有人会被杀死的
You will remain the English gentleman and someone will be killed.
真见鬼 波罗
Oh, dash it all, Poirot.
你有的时候真是顽固 你知道吗 黑斯廷斯
You can be quite obstinate at times. Do you know that, Hastings?
我也希望还有其他我可以信赖的人
I also wish there was someone else I could trust...
但是我想我只能忍受你了
..but I suppose I will have to put up with you.
因为你根本没有灰色脑细胞
And since you cannot use your little grey cells
也不能强迫你用它
because you do not possess them,
但无论如何用用你的眼睛
at any rate use your eyes,
你的耳朵 你的鼻子 如果需要的话
your ears, your nose, if need be.
当然 在尊严允许的范围内
But only, of course, as far as the dictates of honour will allow.
现在走吧
Now go away.
我很累了
I'm very tired.
又来了 你又在
At it again, are you...
练习杀人游戏了吗
at your deadly exercise?
我知道你会的
I knew you would be.
为了我的罪恶 我知道你会的
For my sins, I knew you would.
但只要我一息尚存 我就会...
But while I have breath in my body, I will...
我就会诅咒你下地狱
I will damn you to hell...
不计一切代价
..whatever the cost.
他看起来不太高兴
He doesn't look too happy.
他确实不高兴
He isn't.
他曾有机会前往非洲
He was offered the chance to go to Africa,
继续他的研究 但是他妻子坚决不同意
to continue his research, but his wife protested.
他或许不忍心离开她
He probably felt he couldn't leave her.
你很了解她吗 上校
Do you know much about her, Captain?
我只知道她体弱多病
Only that she's an invalid.
她以生病为乐呢
She certainly enjoys ill health.
所以你认为她的病没那么严重
So you don't think there's very much the matter?
她似乎总是能够如愿以偿
She always seems to be able to do anything she wants.
你和富兰克林夫妇很熟吗
You know the Franklins well, do you?
没有
Er...no.
我刚才说的话 都是从你女儿那里听到的
What I've told you I learnt from your daughter.
她在竭力支持他
She's up in arms on his behalf.
你觉得诺顿先生怎么样
What do you think of Mr Norton?
- 为什么这么问 - 你们关系好像不错
- Why do you ask? - You seem to get on well.
我们有很多共同点
We have a good deal in common,
他非常善良 虽然...不是很机灵
and he's awfully kind, if a little...ineffectual.
他是个斯文的人
No, he's a gentle soul.
他和他母亲住了很多年 她非常专横
He lived with his mother for many years - she was very bossy -
而且我想他在学校里过得也不太好
and I don't think he had a very good time at school either.
他的感觉很敏锐
He's very perceptive, you know.
安静的人一般都这样
Quiet people often are.
是的
Yes.
所以这样的地方才阴沉沉的
That's the depressing thing about places like this.
聚集着失败者
It's full of failures.
我想是因为又经历了一场战争
I suppose it's having endured another war.
我们都曾有过创伤
We've all had the stuffing knocked out of us.
你参与过很多军事行动吗 黑斯廷斯上校
Did you see much action, Captain Hastings?
现在不行了
Oh, not allowed to this time round.
腿脚不好了 而且实话说 我也有点放任
Gammy leg. And, let's face it, I'm pushing it a bit.
但你的人生才刚开始
But your life's just beginning.
一切皆有可能
Anything might happen.
如果你在说婚姻的话 我从不敢去想
If you mean marriage, I could never think of it.
因为我的过去
Not with my history.
什么意思
What do you mean?
你不知道我是谁吧
You have no idea who I am, have you?
我知道你的名字
I know your name.
我不叫科尔 而是利奇菲尔德
It isn't Cole. It's Litchfield.
马修・利奇菲尔德
Matthew Litchfield.
是的 他是我父亲
Yes. He was my father.
他是个恶棍 黑斯廷斯上校
A wicked man, Captain Hastings.
他一直囚禁着我们
He was our jailer
直到我姐姐玛格丽特...
until my sister Margaret...
是的 我知道 报纸上都登了
Yes, I know. It was in all the papers.
但你不知道
But you don't.
我不相信是她杀了他
It's inconceivable she'd murder him.
我知道她投案自首了 但是...
I know she gave herself up, but...
我总觉得这不对劲
...I've always felt it wasn't true.
不是玛格丽特干的
It wasn't Margaret.
不可能
It can't have been.
早上好 先生们
Good morning, gentlemen.
早上好 富兰克林夫人
Good morning, Mrs Franklin.
你今天心情很好啊 夫人
You sound very happy today, madame.
是啊 是啊 波罗先生
I am. I am, Monsieur Poirot.
我要和威廉姆爵士
I'm going on a little outing with Sir William
去奈顿公馆帮他选窗帘
to Knatton Hall to advise him on his cretonnes.
我太笨了 昨天和约翰说话的时候
Silly me left my handbag in the studio yesterday
把包落在工作室了
when I was talking to John.
- 我太健忘了 - 富兰克林医师去哪里了
- Head like a sieve. Where is Dr Franklin?
他和朱蒂丝去塔明斯特
He and Judith have driven into Tadminster
买化学药品和其他一些东西
for some chemical or other.
我真为自己没有一个科研头脑感到庆幸
I'm so glad I don't have a scientific mind.
在这样好的天气 那种行为多么幼稚
On a day like this, it all seems so puerile.
别让科学家们听到你说的这些 夫人
Do not let the scientists hear you say that, madame.
不 你不要以为我不欣赏我的丈夫 先生
Oh. Oh, you mustn't think I don't admire my husband, monsieur.
他对工作那是殚精竭虑
The way he lives for his work is really tremendous,
但我也怕他陷得太深而无法自拔
but it makes me nervous the lengths to which he might go.
你这话是什么意思 夫人
What exactly do you mean, madame?
就是那毒扁豆的事情
Well, this horrible Calabar bean thing.
我很担心他会在自己身上做实验
I'm so afraid he's going to start experimenting on himself.
他只能在动物身上研究到这么多
You see, he can only learn so much from animals.
他一定会做好一切预防措施
He'd take every precaution, surely.
你不了解约翰 他根本不注意自己的安全
Oh, you don't know John. Absolutely oblivious of his own safety.
他真是一个圣人
He really is a sort of saint.
- 准备好了吗 宝贝 - 不能让男爵久等
- You ready, Babs? - Oh. Mustn't keep the baronet waiting.
富兰克林医师 当代圣人
Dr Franklin, the modern saint.
她听风就是雨
She's a feather for every wind.
你觉得她是个傻瓜吗 黑斯廷斯
You think she is a fool, do you not, Hastings?
她反正不是最聪明的人
Well, she's not the most brilliant intellect.
先是她的包 现在又忘了手套
First her handbag, now her gloves.
真不知道那姑娘怎么能受得了她
I don't know how that girl puts up with it.
就差一点啊
It was so close! Wasn't it?
我...发现 上校
I...can't help noticing, Captain,
你看起来有点心神不宁
that you're looking a little uneasy.
- 是吗 - 我不得不说 我也很不安
- Am I? - And I have to say, well, I'd feel the same way.
世道总在变 不是吗
Things change all the time, don't they?
女孩们现在更加自由独立了
Girls are more independent now.
我想很大程度上是因为战争的关系
I suppose the w-war had a lot to do with that.
你想说什么 诺顿
What are you trying to say, Norton?
别想太多 但是...
...don't let it go further, but...
一遇到年轻姑娘
...when it comes to young women,
阿勒顿就特别会耍花样
Allerton has rather a special t-technique in that line.
事实上 我碰巧知道一些他的丑事
I happen to know something pretty f-foul about him, actually.
什么事
And what would that be?
不久以前 我听说一个像朱蒂丝那样的女孩
Not long ago, I heard of a girl just like Judith...
时髦 独立
modern, independent...
掉入了少校的温柔乡
falling prey to the major's charms.
他得手之后
Once he'd got her in his clutches,
就在她最脆弱的时候
just when she was at her most v-vulnerable,
抛弃了她 她很绝望
he abandoned her, leaving her d-desperate.
因为伤心欲绝
So d-devastated was she...
她自杀了
...she took her own life.
吃了大量安眠药
An overdose of Veronal.
可怜的老妇人
Poor old woman.
痛苦不堪
Devilish pain.
过量服用吗啡要了她的性命
Overdose of morphia finished her off
她的侄女弗雷达说是一个疏忽
and her niece, Freda, said it was a slip-up.
警察不这么认为 但没有足够证据来起诉
The police had other ideas but didn't have enough evidence to prosecute.
你认识她 对吗 弗雷达・克莱
You knew her, did you, Freda Clay?
是的
Yes.
我只是以前听过这个事情
It is just that I have heard this story before.
我也听过 还是一个在现场的人告诉我的
So have I, from someone who was there, actually.
是吗
Ah, have you?
报纸上都登了
It was in all the papers.
我脑子有时候 不太灵光
Get a bit erm...fuddled in the old brain-box sometimes.
比尔 你能说点开心的事吗
Oh, Bill, can't you think of anything jollier to talk about?
我想波罗先生一定都吃得倒牙了
I'm sure Monsieur Poirot is fed up to the back teeth
听你们讨论这些杀人 死亡和凶手的事
with people killing and dying and who did what and why.
她倒会让我们保持警惕 对吧 富兰克林
She certainly keeps us on our toes, eh, Franklin?
正合我意
Just the ticket.
不过确实有过报道
They do say, don't they,
说有些男人想娶自己的妈妈
that men tend to marry their mothers?
我不太确定
I'm not quite sure about that.
最好问诺顿 他是专家
Better ask Norton. He's the expert.
大家都来了
A full complement!
真是荣幸 对吗 托比
What a treat! Isn't it, Toby?
是的 我的宝贝
Yes, my sweet.
你可是为我们的晚餐增色不少 波罗先生
Our little dinners are not the same without you, Monsieur Poirot.
是的 我不想让你总一个人吃饭
No. I don't like the thought of your eating alone.
我这个人不喜欢错过任何事 亲爱的
I myself do not like to miss anything, mon cher.
从来都没从工作中抽身休息一下
Never a m-moment's rest in your line of work.
没有 诺顿先生 总有做不完的事情
No, no, Monsieur Norton, there is always still so much more to do...
但时间不多了 对吗
...but the clock it ticks. Non?
这是上帝的意志
Such is the will of God.
我们都会想念你的 老朋友 你会被永远铭记
We'll all miss you, old chap, but you won't be forgotten.
葡萄酒真不错 但我的意思是...
Damn good claret. But my point is...
得了 比尔
Now, Bill.
可以看出弗雷达的本意 是想让某人摆脱痛苦
You can see where Freda was coming from, putting somebody out of their misery.
你们不觉得这样做应当经过病人的同意吗
Don't you think it should only be done with the patient's consent?
不能让病人来做决定
It can't be left to the patient.
应该由爱他们的人来负起这个责任
It's the duty of someone who loves them to take responsibility.
最后却被指控谋杀吗
And end up being charged with murder?
如果你爱一个人 就得冒这个险
If you love someone, you'd take that risk.
- 你会吗 - 是的 我会
- Would you? - Yes, I would.
我肯定不会 托比也不会 你会吗 亲爱的
Well, I certainly wouldn't, and neither would Toby, would you, dear?
喝点水 就没事了
Sip of water. That'll shift it.
不能让法律落入人们的掌控
You can't have people taking the law into their own hands.
我很同意 你觉得呢 富兰克林
I quite agree. What about you, Franklin?
- 什么 - 安乐死
- What? - Euthanasia.
你一定有自己的看法 你可是个医生
You must have an opinion. You're a doctor.
抱歉 我走神了
Mm... Sorry. My mind was elsewhere.
大多数人都没那个勇 勇气
Most people wouldn't have the n-nerve.
如果真到那一天 我不相信你会给人安乐死
I don't believe you would if it came to it.
不会吗
Don't you?
除非 当然 你另有企图
Unless, of course, you had an axe to grind.
你没明白我的意思 是吗
You don't understand, do you?
如果只是为了达到个人目的的话
Of course I couldn't
我当然不会这么做
if the motive was personal.
即便不是 我也不相信
Even if it weren't, I'm not sure
你会真的扣动扳机 可以这么说
you would actually p-pull the trigger, so to speak.
我们能说点别的吗
Can't we talk about something else?
同意 这些太可怕了
I agree. It's all far too grim.
我不像你们那样把生命看得那么神圣
I don't hold life as sacred as you people do.
不健康的生命 无用的生命 就该被除掉
Unfit lives, useless lives...they should be got out of the way.
- 朱蒂丝 - 就应该 那真是一团糟
- Judith! - They should. There's so much mess about.
她也许有点道理
She might have a point.
其实还是勇气的问题
It's really a question of  c-courage.
说的粗俗些 有人有这个胆量吗
Does one have the g-guts, to put it vulgarly?
而且 黑斯廷斯小姐 我觉得你没有
And you see, Miss Hastings, but I don't believe you have.
朱蒂丝还是有胆量的
Oh, Judith's got guts all right.
我有超出你的想象的勇气 诺顿先生
A lot more than you think, Mr Norton.
失陪了
Excuse me.
朱蒂丝
Judith!
我很理解
I do understand, you know.
在这方面你妈妈远比我做得好 但我确实理解
Your mother was so much better at this than I am, but I do understand.
我不觉得你理解
I'm not so sure that you do.
他不值得 相信我 他不值得
He isn't worth it. Believe me, he isn't.
我知道你喜欢他 但是这没好处
I know you care about him, but it's no good.
- 也许我和你一样清楚 - 不会有结果的
- Perhaps I know that as well as you. - It has no future.
他会伤透你的心 我不忍心看你受伤害
He'll break your heart and I can't bear to see that happen.
- 对我来说他比任何事都值得 - 别这样
- He's worth everything in the world to me. - Please.
我不希望你再提起他了
I don't want you ever to speak of him again,
你再说的话 我会更加恨你的
because if you do, I will hate you even more.
这个你也理解吗
Do you understand that?
我第一次见
Well, I never!
一只花斑啄木鸟
A s-speckled woodpecker.
多可爱的小鸟
Such a lovely bird!
- 什么东西 - 飞走了
- What is it? - Flown away.
- 让我看看 - 我...我想是我搞错了
- Let me see. - I...I think I might have made a mistake.
它走了 黑斯廷斯上校
It's gone, Captain Hastings.
怎么了
What's wrong?
那只鸟飞走了
The bird's gone.
- 你们好 朋友们 - 你好 威廉姆爵士
- Hello, you chaps! - Hello, Sir William.
我们度过了一个非常美好的上午
We've had a perfectly marvellous morning.
我好久都没这么开心地购过物了
I haven't been able to do a good shop for simply ages.
比尔 你能把这个拿上去吗
Oh, Bill, could you take that up?
易碎的哦
It's very fragile.
我可以帮你拿其他的
I can bring the rest.
非常感谢
Thanks awfully.
- 有什么事吗 斯蒂文 - 没有
- Anything the matter, Stephen? - No.
- 你看起来像见了鬼一样 - 没 没有鬼
- You look as if you've seen a ghost. - No. No, no ghosts.
只是...在想事情
Just...thinking.
波罗先生
Monsieur Poirot.
怎么了 有麻烦事吗
What is it? Is anything the matter?
麻烦 先生
The matter, monsieur?
什么事是麻烦事
What should be the matter?
我突然觉得好累
Do you know, I'm suddenly terribly tired?
劳驾你把这些搬上去
If you could bring those up...
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
芭布斯
Ah, Babs! Uh...
我必须得说 护士小姐很擅长看手相
Well, I must say, Nurse is very good at the old palm-reading.
拿好这些 克拉文 给我调杯蛋黄酒
Take these, Craven, and fix me an egg-flip.
我好累
I'm exhausted.
我能做什么吗 芭布斯
Can I do anything, Babs?
是的 比尔 你可以消失了
Yes, Bill, you can go away.
我脚都没知觉了
I'm dead on my feet.
走太多路了吗
Has it all been too much for you?
我不想说什么 我不喜欢麻烦别人
I don't want to mention it. I do so hate being tiresome.
我猜今晚有暴风雨 黑斯廷斯
I reckon we're in for a storm tonight, eh, Hastings?
是啊 也许有
Yes, probably right.
- 失陪了 - 想去花园散散步吗
- Excuse me. - Care to take a stroll around the garden?
- 现在不行 诺顿 - 但是 上校...
- Not now, Norton. - But, Captain...
阿勒顿
Allerton.
- 别去 - 放开我
- You can't. - Let go of me!
- 你什么也做不了 - 你倒成家长专家了
- There's nothing you can do. - The expert parent, eh?
- 这样做一点用也没有 - 那就这么定了
- This won't get you anywhere. - That's settled, then.
明天去城里 我就说我去伊普斯威奇呆一两天
Go up to town tomorrow and I'll say I'm off to Ipswich for a night or two.
然后从伦敦发电报 说你赶不回来
Wire from London that you can't make it back
在我的公寓里吃一顿温馨的晚餐
and we'll have a charming little dinner at my flat.
你不会后悔的 我保证
You won't regret it, I promise.
求你了 黑斯廷斯
Please, Hastings.
你需要的是喝一 一大杯威士忌
What you need is a l-large scotch.
败家子回来了
The prodigal returns.
我很抱歉 老朋友 我有点头疼
I'm awfully sorry, old boy. I've got a blinder of a headache.
- 一定是打雷的关系 - 不 不 不
- Must be the thunder in the air. - No, no, no.
那是因为你深陷迷阵
It is because you sit around in the draughts.
- 是吗 - 我很确定
- Is it? - Most assuredly.
那迷阵就是我们所有人的死
The draughts will be the death of us all.
但我有完美解药
But I have just the thing.
热巧克力
The hot chocolate.
它能放松神经 明白吗
It nourishes the nerves. You comprehend?
喝吧 喝吧
Drink, drink.
你已经觉得好点了吧
Do you not already feel much improved?
都喝完 亲爱的朋友 一滴都不要剩
Drink it all, cher ami, every last drop.
天哪 波罗 我在想什么
My God, Poirot, what was I thinking of?
没错
What indeed!
你为什么昨晚不告诉我
Why did you not tell it to me last night?
- 我怕你会阻止我 - 我一定会
- I was afraid you'd stop me. - Most assuredly I would.
你觉得我会眼睁睁看你被绞死吗
Do you think I wish to see you hanged
就为了那个叫阿勒顿的恶棍吗
all on account of a scoundrel so unpleasant called Allerton?
我会把瓶子上的指纹擦掉
Oh, I'd wiped my fingerprints off the bottle.
是的 但也会擦掉阿勒顿的
Yes and also those of Allerton.
然后人们发现他死了 会确认他死于药物过量
And then when he is found dead, they establish that he died of an overdose,
但不管是意外 还是蓄意
and whether by accident or by design,
他都没有理由擦掉他自己的指纹
he would have had no reason to wipe off his own fingerprints.
而且之后
And then...
他们会发现瓶里的阿司匹林
they find the aspirin.
阿司匹林谁都有
Well, everyone has aspirin.
但不是谁都把它和安眠药混在一起
Not mixed with their sleeping pills.
也不是谁都有一个
And not everyone has a daughter
被阿勒顿打无耻盘算的女儿
whom Allerton is pursuing with the intentions so dishonourable.
这会对你非常不利 黑斯廷斯
You see, it would not have looked too good for you, Hastings.
而且也可能会有人看见了你
And then of course it is possible that someone may have seen you.
我保证没人看见
I can assure you they didn't.
也许有人会透过钥匙孔偷看
Someone might have been peeping through the keyhole.
没有人会无聊到透过钥匙孔偷看的
People do not spend their time peeping through keyholes.
这不合常理 总之 我并没真的去做
It's simply not done. Anyway, it didn't come off.
感谢上帝
Thank heavens for that.
但朱蒂丝和阿勒顿之间还是有问题
But there's still the problem of my Judith and Allerton.
她和他今天一起去伦敦了 去他的公寓
She's gone to London with him today - to his flat!
羊入虎口啊
Straight into the lion's den.
黑斯廷斯 你斗不过那两个人的
Hastings, you are not clever enough to deal with those two.
我建议你相信她
I would advise you to trust her.
朱蒂丝
Oh, Judith.
毒药开始蔓延 必须马上制止
The poison works...and must be stopped.
愿主帮助我们
God help us.
愿主帮助我
God help me.
勒特雷尔夫妇会参加吗
Are the Luttrells joining us?
他们在准备纸牌
They're setting up the cards.
黑斯廷斯小姐 你今晚看起来美极了
Miss Hastings, you look s-splendid this evening.
也许是受同名之累 你看起来很像那个
Like your namesake might have appeared
砍掉了赫罗弗尼斯首级之前的犹太人朱蒂丝
before c-cutting off the head of Holofernes.
朱蒂丝是诱惑和杀死亚述统帅赫罗弗尼斯的以色列寡妇
这么说可有点恐怖 老朋友
That's a bit grim, old boy.
不 她这么做完全是基于社会道义
Oh, no, she did it for strictly moral reasons,
为了救其他人
to...to save others.
"嫉妒是绿眼怪兽" 这句话是谁说的
"Jealousy is a green-eyed monster," this person said.
莎士比亚
Shakespeare.
是奥赛罗还是艾米拉说的来着
Oh, now, was that Othello or Emilia?
亚戈・奥赛罗和艾米拉均为莎士比亚《奥赛罗》中的人物
- 是亚戈 - 看 一颗流星
- Iago. - Look! A shooting star!
- 哪儿 - 又有一颗
- Where? - And another one!
你得来看看 赫尔克里叔叔
Oh, you must come and see, Uncle Hercule.
- 不不不 谢谢 - 你一定得看看
- No, no, no, merci. - I insist.
你应该去许个愿 上校
You're supposed to make a wish, Captain.
- 芭布斯 你怎么不过来呢 - 我太累了
- Babs, come on over, why don't you? - Oh, I'm too tired.
胡说 机不可失
Nonsense. It's too good to miss.
比尔 放我下来
Bill! Put me down!
快看啊
Look at that!
你在干嘛
What are you doing?
我想看这儿是不是有一本...
I was just seeing if there was a copy of uh...
我记得妈妈给我讲过
I remember mother told me
你以前曾把她抱到阳台去看星星
how you once carried her out onto a balcony to look at the stars.
找到了
Ah, here we are.
生活有时很艰难 对吗
Life's quite hard at times, isn't it?
《奥赛罗》 哪页来着
Othello. Now...where is it?
"当心 我的主人 嫉妒
"O, beware, my lord, of jealousy;
它是一只绿眼怪兽"
It is a green-ey'd monster..."
美极了
Splendid.
你说对了 波罗 就是亚戈
You were right, Poirot. It was Iago.
那是当然
But of course.
我错过什么了吗
Did I miss anything?
我可不知道 黑斯廷斯 你错过了吗
I do not know, Hastings. Did you?
当然 黑斯廷斯上校
Oh, you did, Captain Hastings.
我从来没见过那么多流星
I've never seen so many shooting stars.
- 克拉文在哪 - 不知道
- Where's Craven? - Not sure.
- 我得吃药了 - 放在哪了
- I need my drops. - Where are they?
在浴室的橱柜里
In the bathroom cabinet.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Oh, thank you, dear.
我出去转转
Think I'll take a stroll.
你似乎很开心啊 医生
You seem pleased with yourself, Doctor.
没错
I am.
你来了 能帮我打开药瓶吗
Oh, there you are. Open my drops, would you?
经鉴定芭芭拉・富兰克林是因为
It is established that Barbara Franklin died
服用了硫酸依色林
as a result of poisoning by physostigmine sulphate
以及一些毒扁豆碱中毒而死
and other alkaloids of the Calabar bean.
波罗先生 你能告诉我们 在你眼里
Monsieur Poirot, could you tell the court
富兰克林夫人在死前的几个小时里
how Mrs Franklin seemed to you in the hours
状态怎么样吗
before her death?
富兰克林夫人去世的前一天
On the day before her death,
我曾和她交谈过
I had a conversation with Madame Franklin.
她看起来非常郁闷
She appeared very depressed...
而且表达了好几次想...
and several times expressed the desire to be...
怎么说来着
How do you say?
摆脱一切
Out of it all.
健康状况和忧郁症
Her health and fits of melancholy
让她的生活看起来失去了意义
made her life seem not to be worth living.
十月十日的早晨 你是不是坐在实验室外面
On the morning of October the 10th, you were sitting outside the laboratory?
是的
Oui.
你看见富兰克林夫人从实验室里出来了吗
Did you see Mrs Franklin come out of the laboratory?
是的 看见了
Yes, I did.
她手上拿着什么东西吗 波罗先生
And did she have anything in her hand, Monsieur Poirot?
她的右手拿着个小瓶子
She had a small bottle clasped in her right hand.
你确定吗
You are quite sure of that?
是的 非常确定
Yes, quite sure.
你也看见了吧
Did you not see it also?
重点是 你看见了没有
The question is, did you?
- 你觉得我在撒谎吗 - 那可是作伪证啊
- You think I would lie? - That would be perjury.
不算 我可没发誓
No, I was not on oath.
所以你确实撒谎了
So it was a lie?
你也亲耳听到了她说她想自杀
You yourself heard her speak of suicide.
但女人总是有很多情绪 你还没调查清楚
But she was a woman of many moods. You didn't clarify that.
也许我只是不想呢
Perhaps I did not wish to.
你是说你想让这起案子判为自杀吗
You mean you wanted the verdict to be suicide?
你知道她是被谋杀的 对吧
You think she was murdered, don't you?
没错
She was.
但这么判的话就不会有更加深入的审讯了
But this verdict stops all further enquiry.
你在耍什么把戏 波罗
What are you playing at, Poirot?
这不是一场游戏 老朋友 我向你保证
This is not a game, mon ami, I assure you.
不 不
No, no.
说实话 老伙计 你真的得看医生了
I must say, old man, you really should see a doctor.
东一句医生 西一句医生
Doctors, doctors!
你看起来很糟糕
You are looking pretty ropey.
他们该做的都已经做了
They've done all they can for me.
我倒希望你也是
I do wish you would.
好吧 好吧
Very well, very well.
- 我就见富兰克林医师 - 富兰克林
- I will see Dr Franklin. - Franklin?
黑斯廷斯 照我说的做 就这一次
Hastings, just do as I tell you - for once.
- 他怎么样 - 恐怕快不行了
- How is he? - He's for it, I'm afraid.
他知道吗
Does he know?
知道 我觉得他一直在担心
Oh, yes. I gather he's worried about
有件事情还没做完
getting something finished.
- 没错 - 我希望他能早日完成
- That's right. - Then I hope he does.
- 没有什么治疗吗 - 不需要
- Isn't there any treatment? - Nothing doing.
当他的心绞痛发作时
Just his ampoules of amyl nitrite
及时服用安亚硝酸戊酯就行了
when he feels angina coming on.
他是个很出色的人
A remarkable man.
他很尊崇人类的生命 对吗
He has a great respect for human life, hasn't he?
- 是啊 当然 - 不像我
- Yes, absolutely. - Unlike me.
反正人必有一死 又有什么要紧呢
Since death comes anyway, what's it matter?
- 我得出差十天 - 去哪
- Oh, well, ten days and I'm off. - Where to?
非洲
Africa.
工作还要继续
The job's still open.
这也太快了吧
Isn't that rather soon?
还有什么能牵绊我的吗
What's to stop me?
我也没什么好装
It's no good pretending
芭芭拉的死其实是最好的解脱
that Barbara's death wasn't the greatest relief.
判她自杀你难道不觉得奇怪吗
It doesn't worry you that she's just committed suicide?
不过我还真觉得她不会自杀
But I don't really believe she did.
那你觉得是怎么回事
Then what do you think happened?
我不知道
I don't know...
也不想知道
and I don't want to know.
明白了吗
Understand?
诺顿 到底怎么了
Norton, what's the matter?
要判定一件事之是或非
when a thing's right or wrong,
应该很容易 不是吗
it should be awfully simple to say so, shouldn't it?
- 你懂我的意思吗 - 不懂
- Do you see what I mean? - No.
我想说 说的是...
What I'm t-trying to say is...
比如 你不小心拆了一封
say, for example, you happened to open
别人的信
a letter that wasn't yours
当然是误拆
by mistake, of course -
或者是 从钥匙孔看见了一些东西 懂吗
or...or s-saw something - through a k-keyhole, say?
- 一个钥匙孔 - 没错
- A keyhole? - Yes.
你为什么要从钥匙孔里偷看
Why on earth would you be looking through a keyhole?
也许因为钥匙卡住了
The key might have got stuck.
别拐弯抹角了 你从钥匙孔里看见了什么
Stop beating about the bush. Did you see something through a keyhole?
没有
No.
但你从那副望远镜里看见了什么吧
But you did see something through those glasses of yours?
我们陪科尔小姐出去散步的那天
That day we went out rambling with Miss Cole,
有什么东西你不想让我看见 对吗
there was something you didn't want me to see, wasn't there?
是 没有
Yes. Well...no.
是什么东西
What was it?
我不知道该不该说
I...don't know if I ought to say.
我是无意看到的
I didn't m-mean to see it.
确实有一只斑 斑点啄木鸟
There really was a s-speckled woodpecker -
很可爱的家伙
lovely fellow -
然后我看见了其他东西
then I saw the other thing.
是不是和富兰克林夫人的死有关
Is it to do with Mrs Franklin's death?
真该死
Oh, damn it all.
我不知道该怎么做
I don't know what to do.
- 他看见了什么却不想告诉你吗 - 没错
- He saw something that he will not tell to you? - That's right.
- 他有没有告诉其他人 - 应该没有
- Has he told this to anyone else? - I don't think so.
吃过晚饭叫他来见我
Ask him to come up and see me after dinner.
就说是一次朋友间的会面
Just a friendly little visit.
小心点 黑斯廷斯
And be careful, Hastings.
要非常小心
Be very careful.
我明天就要搬回自己的老宅子了
I'm moving back to my old pile tomorrow.
实话告诉你 我很高兴能尽快摆脱这个鬼地方
I don't mind telling you, I'll be glad to be shot of this place.
这儿让有点阴森森的 比如可怜的芭布斯
It gives me the creeps. Poor Babs, for instance.
如果她真是自杀 我的名字就倒着写
If she killed herself, then I'm a monkey's uncle.
你知道我怎么想的吗
You know what I think?
我觉得是她丈夫干的
I think it was that husband of hers.
- 不是吧 - 而且不止我一个人这么想
- You don't mean that. - And I'm not the only one.
从知情人那得到的情报
Had the tip from someone who ought to know.
说曹操 曹操就到
Talk of the devil.
我以为她参加完葬礼就走了
I thought she'd left after the funeral.
她在交接新病人之前 回这儿来过个夜
She's back for the night, between engagements.
波罗先生
Monsieur Poirot?
波罗
Poirot?
进来
Entrez.
你还好吗 老朋友
How are you, old chap?
还没死
Not dead yet.
- 你和诺顿聊得还好吗 - 很好
- Did you have a good chat with Norton? - Oui.
- 他告诉你他看到了什么吗 - 说了
- And he told you what he saw? - Oui.
他看到了什么
Well...what was it?
- 你会误会的 - 我当然不会
- You might misunderstand. - Of course, I won't.
他告诉我他看见了两个人
He tells to me that he saw two people.
朱蒂丝和阿勒顿 我就知道
Judith and Allerton! I knew it!
看吧 不 不是朱蒂丝和阿勒顿
You see? No, not Judith and Allerton!
你脑子里装的全是猪油吧
You have lard for a brain.
这么说可真有点难听
That's a bit harsh.
- 喝水 - 不用了 谢谢
- Drink. - No, thanks.
我要喝
For me!
抱歉
Oh, sorry.
万一发生了什么...
Now, if anything should happen...
不会有什么事发生的 波罗
Nothing will happen to you, Poirot.
你会在这儿找到所有你要的线索
You will find in here all the clues you need...
- 用这个 - 什么样的线索
- with this. - What kind of clues?
会带领你找到真相的指示
Indications that will lead you to the truth.
为什么你要把事情搞得这么复杂
Why do you have to make things so difficult?
我完全蒙在鼓里
I'm completely in the dark as it is!
放心吧 老朋友
Rest assured, mon ami,
当真相来临时 你会宁愿自己不知道
when you see the light... you may wish you had not.
现在我需要思考
And now I need to think.
- 但是 波罗 - 去吃早饭吧 老朋友
- But, Poirot... - Go down to breakfast, mon ami.
- 这个案子已经了结了 - 是吗
- The case, it is ended. - Is it?
只需要再整理一些细节
Only loose ends to be tied.
- 你今天起晚了嘛 - 我没有睡好
- You're late up this morning. - I didn't get much sleep.
你看见诺顿了吗 他没来吃早饭
Have you seen Norton? He wasn't at breakfast.
他反锁了门 我听见了
He locked the door. I heard him.
他朝自己开枪了吗
He shot himself?
没错 他们是这么说的
Well, that's what they're saying.
门上了锁 钥匙在他的口袋里 枪在他手上
The door was locked, the key was in his pocket, the gun was in his hand.
我想只能是他自己干的了
I suppose he must have done.
就像个魔术的把戏 不是吗
It is like a conjuring trick, n'est-ce pas?
黑斯廷斯
Hastings,
有时候你就像个小孩
sometimes you are like a little child,
太天真 太轻信别人...
so innocent, so trusting...
波罗 你看起来非常糟糕
Poirot, you're looking pretty awful.
我是不是该找个医生
Don't you think I should call a doctor?
那又怎样呢
What good would that do?
该来的还是会来
What will be will be.
我总是竭尽我所能
I have always tried to do my best, you know.
你相信吗 黑斯廷斯
You do believe that, Hastings?
我怎会不信呢
How could I not?
你觉得上帝会原谅我吗
Do you think God will forgive me?
他当然会原谅你
Of course he'll forgive you.
你是个好人 是我认识的最好的人
You're a good man - the best a fellow could know.
我对你深表同情
My heart bleeds for you,
我可怜的孤独的黑斯廷斯
my poor, lonely Hastings.
- 波罗 - 出去吧 我亲爱的朋友
- Poirot... - Go now, cher ami.
让我休息一下
Let me rest.
那不是自杀
It was not suicide.
是谋杀
It was murder.
亲爱的朋友
Cher ami...
原谅我
Forgive me.
原谅…
Forgive...
黑斯廷斯上校
Captain Hastings?
这是迟早的事
It was bound to happen.
即便这样也并不好受
That doesn't make it any easier.
不
No.
当然不会
No, of course, it doesn't.
说是自然原因
Natural causes.
我很怀疑
I wonder.
你不是在暗示有什么阴谋吧
You're not suggesting foul play, I hope?
看起来似乎很不可能 对吧
It doesn't seem very likely, does it?
爸爸 他是心脏病发了
Father, he had a heart attack.
尽管如此
All the same...
任何事都可能引起他病发
Anything could have triggered it -
也可能是毫无缘故
or perhaps nothing.
也许他的大限已到
Perhaps his time had come.
他肯定不像可怜的诺顿先生一样是自杀
And it surely wasn't suicide, like poor Mr Norton.
他们说是因为投资失败
Bad investments, so they say.
验尸官觉得
The coroner did think it strange
他能开枪打自己前额中心很奇怪
that he would shoot himself in the centre of his forehead.
你真是多疑
What a suspicious soul you are!
我想是因为这些年和波罗在一起吧
All those years with Poirot, I expect.
他是我最亲近的朋友
He was my dearest friend, you know.
他总是在那里 监督我 责备我
He was always there, keeping an eye on me, ticking me off...
真的就像位父亲
..like a father, really.
我真不知道没了他该怎么办
I'm not quite sure how I'll cope without him.
爸爸 有些话我想和你说
Father, I have something to tell you.
亲爱的 我不喜欢这种语气
Oh, dear. I don't like the sound of that.
之前事情一件接一件的 我就没有告诉你
I haven't told you before, what with one thing and another,
但事实上 我打算去非洲
but the fact is, I'm going to Africa.
非洲
Africa?
是的 和富兰克林医生一起
Yes, with Dr Franklin.
你不能去 人们会怎么说
You can't do that. What will people say?
我不在乎别人说什么 我就是要去
I don't care what people say. The fact is, I'm going.
他妻子在世时 你做他助手是一回事
It's one thing to be his assistant here with his wife alive,
他妻子死之后
but going to Africa
你和他一起去非洲就另当别论了
with him now she's dead.
我去不是做他的助手 而是做他的妻子
I'm not going as his assistant. I'm going as his wife.
但...阿勒顿呢
But...what about Allerton?
我们什么事都没有
There was never anything in that.
如果你没惹我生气的话 我就早点告诉你了
I'd have told you if you hadn't made me so angry.
- 但我看到他吻你了 - 这有什么奇怪的
- But I saw him kiss you. - These things happen.
你不能嫁给富兰克林 现在还不行 太快了
You can't marry Franklin. Not yet. It's so soon.
我能 我也会这么做的
I can and I will.
但是朱蒂丝...
But, Judith...
我们没理由再等了
We've nothing to wait for now!
当真相来临时 你会宁愿自己没有看到
When you see the light, you may wish you had not.
《奥赛罗》
"去找我的贴身男仆 乔治"
我想波罗先生给你留下了什么口信吧
I believe Monsieur Poirot left you some sort of message.
- 口信吗 先生 - 对 给我的
- Message, sir? - Yes, for me.
没有 先生 我不知道
No, sir, not that I'm aware of.
你确定吗
Are you quite sure?
是的 先生 我不记得有
Yes, sir, I'd remember that.
我想是我记错了
My mistake, I suppose.
你父亲怎么样
How is your father?
我父亲
My father?
他很好 谢谢你 先生
He's very well, thank you, sir.
他现在好些了吧
Oh, he's better, then?
什么好些了 先生
Better than what, sir?
你不是因为要去照顾你父亲
That's why you had to leave Monsieur Poirot,
才不得不离开波罗先生的吗
wasn't it, to look after him?
不是我想离开的 先生
I didn't want to leave, sir.
是波罗先生打发我走的
Monsieur Poirot sent me away.
他为什么要这么做呢
Why would he do that?
我只能说他打发我走 是因为想雇佣柯蒂斯
I can only suggest that he discharged me because he wanted to engage Curtis.
- 但为什么呢 - 我真的不知道 先生
- But why? - I really couldn't say, sir.
尽管他很强壮 却不是很聪明
Not the brightest specimen, although he was strong, of course.
但我没想到 波罗先生会喜欢他这种人
But I'd hardly have thought he was quite the class Monsieur Poirot would have liked.
他曾在一家精神病院中做助手
He'd been an assistant in a mental home.
精神病院
A mental home?
就算他是那儿的病人 我也不会惊讶
It wouldn't surprise me if he'd started off there as a patient.
四个月后
我已经通知我的律师们
I have instructed my lawyers...
在我死后四个月
..to deliver this manuscript to you...
把这份手稿给你
..four months after my death...
那时你肯定已经有一套最荒谬的理论了
..by which time you will no doubt have evolved the most preposterous theories.
但是真的 我的朋友 你现在应该
But really, mon ami, you should by now
已经能找出是谁杀了诺顿
have been able to work out who killed Norton.
就像杀死芭芭拉・富兰克林的人
As to who killed Barbara Franklin,
一样会令人惊讶
that may come as more of a shock.
当你问我是否知道谁是凶手时
When you asked if I knew who was the killer,
我没有和你说实话
I did not quite tell to you the truth.
我是知道的 但要确定一下
I knew, but had to make sure.
我之前从没见过这种人
You see, I had never met this person before
查案时也没见过
and had never seen this person in action.
这并没有花费我很长时间
It did not take me long.
最终 在我事业的尾声
At last, at the end of my career,
我遇到了最完美的罪犯
I had come across the perfect criminal -
不 是近乎完美
well, nearly perfect.
一对林 林莺在枫树上搭了巢
Pair of n-nesting b-blackcaps down by the sycamore.
没人能超过赫尔克里・波罗
No-one gets the better of Hercule Poirot.
即使是斯蒂文・诺顿
Not even Stephen Norton.
我真是…
Well, I'll be...
是的 诺顿就是我们要找的人
Oh, yes, Norton was our man.
他曾是个病弱的男孩 有个专横的母亲
He had been a sickly boy with a domineering mother,
他在学校的时光也很艰难
he had had a hard time at school,
不喜欢血腥与暴力
and disliked blood and violence -
一个最不像英国人的特点
a trait most un-English.
但他富有同情心
But he had a sympathetic character
而且很快就发现 要利用它有多么容易
and soon discovered how easy it was to make use of it.
通过理解人们 他能洞悉他们最隐秘的想法
By understanding people, he could penetrate their innermost thoughts...
他十分敏锐 安静的人通常如此
He's very perceptive, you know. Quiet people often are.
然后他使人们做他们并不想做的事
..and then make them do things they did not want to -
以避免终身受人嘲笑
compensation for a lifetime of derision.
这种权力感逐渐发展成了一种
This sense of power gradually developed
对间接暴力的病态癖好
into a morbid taste for violence at second-hand,
很快又变成了一种痴迷
which soon turned into an obsession.
我们斯文的诺顿其实是一个
Our gentle Norton was in fact
耽于痛苦和精神折磨的施虐狂
a sadist addicted to pain and mental torture.
记得你第一晚玩桥牌时他说的话吗
Remember the remarks he made that first evening you played bridge?
看他这样被欺负真叫我恼火
It gets my back up to see him b-bullied like that.
小点声
Keep it down.
诺顿是故意让他听见的
Norton meant him to hear.
不过就算想反抗 他也无能为力
Couldn't assert himself if he tried.
有时成功 有时失败
Sometimes successful, sometimes not,
就像毒品一样 时刻让他着迷
it was a drug he constantly craved.
没有动机 没有迹象 没有证据
No motive, no evidence, no proof.
仅仅是出于邪恶
Simply evil for the sake of it.
一个永不能被定罪的罪犯
A criminal who could never be convicted of his crimes.
你现在应该知道了
You will have realised by now that
富兰克林和朱蒂丝才是两情相悦的
Franklin was in love with Judith and she with him.
但富兰克林夫人在世时
But with Madame Franklin alive,
朱蒂丝很痛苦
life was very difficult for Judith,
而诺顿完全知道风是怎么刮的
and Norton knew exactly how the wind lay.
他很聪明地利用了无用的生命这个话题
He played most cleverly on the theme of useless lives.
我对待生命并不像你们那么神圣
I don't hold life as sacred as you people do.
病弱的生命 无用的生命 都应该被除掉
Unfit lives, useless lives - they should be got out of the way.
轻微地嘲讽她不会有胆量
And gently ridiculed the idea
根据她的观点 来采取果断的行动
that she would ever have the nerve to take decisive action.
说的粗俗些 有人有这个胆量吗
Does one have the g-guts, to put it vulgarly?
而且 黑斯廷斯小姐 我不认为你有
And you see, Miss Hastings, I don't believe you have.
但是对于一个杀人狂来说
But with a murder addict,
光在一处煽风点火是不够的
one iron in the fire, it is not enough.
他到处寻找可以利用的机会
He sees opportunities for pleasure everywhere,
而且在你身上也找到了一个 我的朋友
and found one in you, mon ami.
他发现了你所有的弱点
He discovered every weak spot
来激化你对阿勒顿少校的厌恶
to exacerbate your profound dislike of Major Allerton.
对于年轻的女士
When it comes to young women,
阿勒顿总有特殊的能力来讨她们欢心
Allerton has rather a special t-technique in that line.
然后你看到了阿勒顿和朱蒂丝拥吻
Then you saw Allerton and Judith kiss.
你不能去
You can't.
诺顿拉走了你
Norton hauled you away
于是你没有看到后来发生了什么
so that you did not see what followed.
你去了暖房
You went to the glass house and
以为你听到了阿勒顿和朱蒂丝的谈话
thought you heard Allerton talking to Judith.
然后从伦敦发电报 说你赶不回来
Wire from London that you can't make it back
我们就在我的公寓里享受令人陶醉的晚餐
and then we'll have a charming little dinner at my flat.
但你没看到她 甚至也没听到她说话
Yet you did not see her or even hear her speak.
诺顿确保了这一点
Norton made sure of that,
因为如果你听到了
for if you had, you would have discovered
你就不会对朱蒂丝那天去伦敦的事有疑问
that there had never been any question of Judith going to London that day.
和他有私情的是克拉文护士
It was Nurse Craven with whom he was having the affair.
但你一头栽进了诺顿的陷阱里
But you fell headlong into the trap of Norton
还萌生了谋杀的念头
and made up your mind to murder.
那晚我听到你上楼来
I heard you come up that evening
已经准备实施你的想法
and was already exercised about your state of mind.
所以当我听到你在走廊
So when I heard you in the corridor...
并走进阿勒顿的卧室时
and go into the bathroom of Allerton,
我溜出了我的房间
I slipped out of my room.
溜出了你的房间?
Slipped out of your room?
但是...
But...
"怎么做到的" 我听到你问
"How?" I hear you say.
黑斯廷斯 我并没丧失这个能力
You see, Hastings, I was not helpless at all.
什么
What?
你觉得我为什么要打发走乔治呢
Why do you think I sent George away?
因为我骗不过他
Because I could not have fooled him into believing
我突然丧失行动能力了
that I had suddenly lost the use ofcmy limbs.
我听到你进了阿勒顿的卧室
I heard you in the bathroom of Allerton
敏捷地 用你强烈谴责的方式
and promptly, in the manner you so much deplore,
跪了下来
dropped to my knees.
我意识到了你将要做什么 我做了准备
I realised what you were up to, made my preparations...
让柯蒂斯来找你
..and sent Curtis to fetch you.
很抱歉 老伙计 我有些头疼
I'm awfully sorry, old boy. I've got a blinder of a headache.
于是我给了你一杯热可可
So I gave to you the hot chocolate.
它可以舒缓你的神经 明白吗
It nourishes the nerves. You comprehend?
喝吧 喝吧
Drink, drink.
但是我的朋友 我还放了些安眠药在里面
But I also, mon ami, have sleeping pills.
不 不 把剩下的都喝完
No, no, no, every last drop.
等你第二天早上醒来的时候 你又恢复了本性
When you awoke the next morning, you were your own self again,
为你差点要做的事情感到后怕
horrified at what you had nearly done.
但这使我下了决心 黑斯廷斯
But it decided me, Hastings.
你不是个杀人犯
You are not a murderer,
但可能会因为一个杀人犯而被绞死
but might have been hanged for one.
我知道我不能再拖了 必须有所行动
I knew that I must act and could put it off no longer,
但在我行动之前 芭芭拉・富兰克林死了
but before I was able to, Barbara Franklin died,
我觉得你不曾怀疑过这件事的真相
and I do not think that you have once suspected the truth.
因为黑斯廷斯 是你杀了她
For you see, Hastings, you killed her.
- 我杀了她? - 对 我的朋友 就是你
- I killed her? - Oui, mon ami, you did.
因为在这个三角关系中 还有另一角
There was, you see, yet another angle to the triangle,
我没有考虑进去
one that I had not fully taken into account.
你可曾想过
Did it ever enter your mind
为什么富兰克林夫人愿意来斯泰尔庄园
why Madame Franklin was willing to come to Styles?
她喜欢舒适的生活
She enjoys the good life,
但却坚持住在一家民宿里
yet insisted on staying in a guest house,
我肯定诺顿知道为什么
and I have no doubt that Norton knew why.
- 你们好 伙计们 - 波伊德・卡灵顿
- Hello, you chaps! - Boyd Carrington.
富兰克林夫人很失望
Madame Franklin was a disappointed woman.
她本以为富兰克林医生会有出色的事业
She had expected Dr Franklin to have a brilliant career...
我们得去... 失陪了
There was something we had to... Do excuse me.
而不是关起门来做难懂的实验
..not shut himself away in esoteric research.
而波伊德・卡灵顿 富有 气派
And here is Boyd Carrington, rich and aristocratic,
在她年轻时差点向她求婚
who had nearly asked to marry her when she was a girl,
现在仍在追求她
still paying court.
所以唯一的办法 就是让他丈夫死
So the only way was for her husband to die,
而诺顿发现她是个很好的工具
and Norton had found her only too ready a tool.
这些搞科学的人对他们的工作如此痴迷
These scientist chaps can get quite obsessive about their work.
这很明显
It was so obvious -
她对这种赞赏的反感
her protestations of admiration,
还有她对她丈夫的恐惧
then her fears for her husband.
他研究的东西让我很不安
But it makes me nervous the lengths to which he might go.
具体是什么呢 夫人
What exactly do you mean, madame?
就是那个可怕的卡拉巴豆
Well, this horrible Calabar bean thing.
我很害怕他会拿自己做实验
I'm so afraid he's going to start experimenting on himself.
但当她看到克拉文护士
But when she saw Nurse Craven
给波伊德・卡灵顿看手相时 她很惊恐
reading the palm of Boyd Carrington, she had a fright.
她知道他会受到迷人女士的魅力影响
She knew he would be susceptible to the charms of an attractive woman
有可能克拉文护士最后会取代她
and perhaps Nurse Craven might end up
成为波伊德・卡灵顿的女人
as Lady Boyd Carrington instead of her.
所以她决定要快点采取行动
So she decided to act quickly.
她邀请我们都去她的房间喝咖啡
She invites us all up to her room for coffee.
她的杯子在她旁边 她丈夫的在另一边
Her cup is beside her and that of her husband is on the other side.
看 流星
Look, a shooting star!
然后所有人都去看流星了
Then everyone goes to watch the shooting stars
除了你 我的朋友
except you, mon ami,
和你的字谜与回忆留在了房间里
left with your crossword and your memories.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
你转动书架 装作在找一本书
You hide your emotion by swinging round the bookcase
以此隐藏自己的情绪
as if looking for a book.
因此当我们回来的时候
And so when we all return,
富兰克林夫人喝下了那杯
Madame Franklin drinks the poisoned coffee
原本为她丈夫所准备的毒咖啡
meant for her husband,
而他则喝掉了原属于她的咖啡
and he drinks the coffee meant for her.
我知道 在那杯毒咖啡
I realised what must have happened,
以及你不经意地转动桌子之间一定有联系
that she had poisoned the coffee and you had unwittingly turned the table,
但黑斯廷斯 我没办法证实
but you see, Hastings, I could not prove it.
如果富兰克林夫人的死
If the death of Madame Franklin
被看做是他杀 而不是自杀
was thought to be anything but suicide,
嫌疑自然而然地便落到了
suspicion would inevitably fall on
富兰克林或朱蒂丝的头上
either Franklin or Judith.
这便是我一直坚持
That is why I was so insistent
富兰克林夫人是自杀的原因
that Madame Franklin had killed herself,
并且我知道大家一定会听从我的意见
and I knew that my statement would be accepted
因为我是赫尔克里・波罗
because I am Hercule Poirot.
你为此感到不满意
You were not pleased,
但幸好你并未怀疑真正的危机
but mercifully you did not suspect the true danger.
当我走了以后 你是否曾想过
Will it come into your mind after I am gone,
就像有一条毒蛇不时出现在你脑海里说
like some dark serpent that now and then raises its head and says,
"假如 只是假如 凶手会不会是朱蒂丝"
"Suppose, just suppose, it was my Judith?"
因此你一定要寻找答案
And therefore you must know the truth.
有一个人对陪审团的裁决
There was one person most unhappy
感到最不满意 就是诺顿
with the verdict - Norton.
他血淋淋的算盘打错了
He was deprived, you see, of his pound of flesh.
确实 富兰克林夫人死了
Madame Franklin had died, yes...
但并不是以他想要的方式
..but not how he desired.
他一手安排的谋杀出了差错
The murder he had arranged had gone awry,
该怎么办呢
so what to do?
诺顿 发生什么事了
Norton, what's the matter?
他便开始谈起那天 与你和科尔小姐在一起时
He began to throw out hints about what he saw that day
所看到的情景
with you and Mademoiselle Cole.
怎么了
What is it?
他从来没有做过具体的描述
He had never said anything definite,
因此如果他能扭转你的印象
so if he could convey the impression
让你以为当天他看到的是富兰克林和朱蒂丝
that it was Franklin and Judith that he saw,
而不是阿勒顿和朱蒂丝时
not Allerton and Judith,
他就能让你从另一个有趣的角度
then that could open up an interesting new angle
看待这次自杀案件
on the suicide case,
甚至能对裁决提出质疑
perhaps even throw doubts on the verdict.
此时我明白 我一直以来准备的计划
And I realised that what I had planned all along
必须马上实施
had to be done at once,
那是我感到最担心的一刻
the moment I had dreaded -
也是我人生中最困难的一次决定
the most difficult decision of my life.
因此那晚我邀请诺顿到我的房间
That is why I invited Norton to my room that night
告诉他我所知道的一切
and told to him all that I knew.
康士坦次・埃瑟林顿夫人 想要毒死她丈夫
Madame Constance Etherington... tried for the poisoning of her husband,
一个身为虐待狂的瘾君子
a man who was very sadistic but also addicted to the drugs
也是与你关系很密切的人
and with whom you are on terms most intimate.
诺拉・夏尔普
Norah Sharples -
被自己的侄女弗雷达・克莱下毒
poisoned by her niece, Freda Clay.
希望你不是认为我和她的关系也很密切
I hope you're not s-suggesting I was on intimate terms with her.
这是你和克莱小姐在一起散步
You and Mademoiselle Clay taking a walk together.
我也是做好功课的 诺顿先生
You see, I do my homework, Monsieur Norton.
还有马修・利奇菲尔德
And Matthew Litchfield.
当他被女儿玛格丽特谋杀的那晚
You visited him, did you not,
你不是去拜访他了吗
on the night he was killed by his daughter, Margaret?
你想说明什么 波罗先生
What is your p-point, Monsieur Poirot?
诺顿先生 我想要说的是
Ah. My point is this, Monsieur Norton.
这些谋杀案都没有什么疑点
That in none of these murders was there any real doubt.
都有一个明显的嫌疑犯 没有其他人
There was one clear suspect. No other.
但是你 诺顿先生
But you, Monsieur Norton...
你是这些案件之间唯一的可怕的共同点
are the one factor malevolent common to all.
天 天哪 波罗先生
Oh, d-dear, Monsieur Poirot,
难道你的小脑袋瓜只能得出这样的结论吗
is that the best your little grey cells can come up with?
你和这三个杀人犯的亲近程度有点太过巧合
Your proximity to these three murders was too much of a coincidence
而且我闻到了 你所说的 老鼠的味道
and I smelt, as you say, the rat.
这是我来斯泰尔庄园的原因
That is why I came to Styles -
是为了来观察你 而你并没有让我失望 先生
to observe you function and you have not disappointed, monsieur.
你是一个非常聪明的人
No. You are a man who is very clever...
可是还不足以对付赫尔克里・波罗
..but not clever enough for...Hercule Poirot.
那你打算怎么做
So...what are you going to d-do about it?
将你处死
Execute you.
将我处死
Execute me?
是的
Oui.
那...请你动手吧
Then...do get on with it.
我今晚可是打算早睡觉的
I promised myself an early night.
正义不是玩笑 先生
Justice is no joking matter, monsieur.
我会尽我最大的能力去维护它
I do what I can to serve it,
一旦我失败了
but if I fail,
你将会受到更严重的惩罚 相信我
there is a justice that is higher, believe me.
你这可怜的自大的小人
You p-pathetic, self-important little man.
想杀了我
Murder me?
你内心的罪恶便会跟随你一辈子
There's a m-mortal sin if ever there was.
接着呢
And then what?
上吊自杀 以此逃避罪恶吗
Suicide to escape the ignominy of hanging?
上帝可是会好好款待你的
Your God will give you a hell of a time.
这么多年来的虔诚 都会因我而化为乌有
All those years of piety up in smoke because of me.
先生
Uh-uh-uh, monsieur.
你还不能死
You can't go yet.
我怎么会让你死在我手上
You don't think I'd let you d-die on me,
就 就此结束我无尽的胜利呢
d-d-deprive me of my ultimate t-triumph?
求你...求你...
Please... Please...
如果你不能成功 那我就是自由人
You see, if you don't succeed, I'm a free man.
即使你成功了 我也并没有输
Even if you do, it would still be a victory of sorts,
因为在法律的眼里 我还是清白的
because in the eyes of the law I would be innocent.
可是你 以及你的声誉
Whereas you and your reputation -
你那宝 宝贵的声誉
your p-precious reputation -
便化为灰烬
blown to bits.
- 求你了 - 求你了
- Je vous en prie. - Je vous en prie.
你听到他们说了吗
You can see them now:
"他疯了 外国人永远都不可信"
"Went off his rocker. You can never trust a foreigner."
发现我对你有多好了吗 老家伙
You see how good I am to you, old man?
这就对了
There you go.
慢慢来
Take your time...
让我们一起来看看最后谁会成功 好吗
and see how it all...pans out, shall we?
谁将会拉下最后的帷幕
Who will be there at the final curtain?
我为你感到可怜 诺顿
I pity you, Norton.
在如此美好的世界里
How very sad to find that this great and beautiful world
你看到的只有腐烂和失望
is so foul and disappointing.
还有你母亲
And your mother...
我更为她感到可怜
I pity even more.
我的母 母亲 你为她感到可怜
My m-mother? You pity my mother?
忍受着带你出生的痛苦
To endure the agony of bringing you forth
却发现她所孕育的是一个变态
only to discover that she had nurtured in her loins such wickedness.
难道这不值得可怜吗
Is that not worthy of pity?
是你不值得可怜
It is you who is not worthy.
她对我来 来说就是整个世界
She m-meant the world to me.
那你对于她来说呢
And you to her?
她爱 爱我
She l-loved me...
她非 非常爱我 甚 甚至...
..l-loved me more than...m-more than...
她是否曾像母亲一样拥抱你 诺顿
Did she ever hold you, Norton, as mothers do,
轻抚你的头发 亲吻你的脸颊
stroke your hair...kiss your cheek?
她... 她...
She... She...
害怕你 对吗
Scared you, did she not?
她把你从身边推开
She pushed you away,
不给予你一丝人间最温暖的情感
starved you of what we all desire,
因为她知道关于你的一切
because she knew everything about you.
我母亲什么都不知道
My mother knew nothing.
诺顿先生 母亲们都知道
Oh, Monsieur Norton, mothers know.
她们一直都知道
They always know.
毫无根据 波罗
Shots in the dark, Poirot.
毫无根据
Shots in the dark.
喝点热巧克力吗
Chocolate?
我可以喝你的那杯吗
Would you mind awfully if I drank yours instead?
当然可以
Not at all.
这对我无关紧要
It was quite immaterial.
我睡前都需要吃安眠药 因此具有一定耐药性
I take the sleeping tablets and have acquired a certain tolerance.
那些能让诺顿沉睡的药
The dose that would send Norton to sleep
对我而言没有多大影响
would have little effect on me.
我费了很大力气 把他挪到我的轮椅上
With the greatest of difficulty, I put him in my wheelchair.
趁没人的时候 我把他推到了他的房间
Then when the coast was clear I wheeled him to his room.
你或许还没有发现 黑斯廷斯
You will not have realised, Hastings,
最近我一直戴着假胡须
that recently I have taken to wearing the false moustache.
这点连乔治也不知道
Even George does not know that.
我穿了诺顿的睡袍
I put on the dressing gown of Norton...
去敲了敲你的门
..tapped on your door...
接着走进他的浴室
..then went into his bathroom.
不久便听到你的开门声
Presently I heard you open your door.
我离开了浴室 回到诺顿的房间
I left the bathroom and returned to the room of Norton,
锁上了门
locking the door behind me.
为诺顿穿上长袍
I put the dressing gown on Norton...
把他放到床上
..and lay him on his bed.
我有一把手枪
I had a pistol,
曾经有两次
which on two occasions
趁他出门的时候 我将手枪放在他梳妆台上
I had placed ostentatiously on the dressing table of Norton
显眼的地方
when he was out,
这样女佣便会看到
so that the maid would have seen it.
我把钥匙放在了他的长袍口袋里
I put the key into the pocket of his dressing gown
用我复制的另一把钥匙 从门外锁了门
and locked the door from the outside with a duplicate I had made...
接着回到了我的房间 写下这封信
..then returned to my room and began writing this.
正如你们英国人所说 我按章办事
I played the game, as you English say.
我给了你所有的线索和机会去发现真相
I gave to you the clues and every chance to discover the truth,
把你指向亚戈 原版的斯蒂文・诺顿
pointing you towards Iago, the original Stephen Norton.
我唯一的缺点 是在他的额头中间开了枪
My only weakness was to shoot him in the centre of
而不是在太阳穴
his forehead and not in his temple,
但我不想使自己造成如此出乎意料的效果
but I could not bring myself to produce an effect so lopsided.
而这些 我的朋友 就是我的本性
That, mon ami, is my nature
也是要告诉你的真相
and should have told to you the truth.
最后再听一次我的建议
Take my advice for the last time.
将我所说的一切告诉科尔小姐
Tell to Mademoiselle Cole all that I have said,
告诉她你也差点做了和她姐姐一样的事
that you also might have done what her sister did...
如果没有谨慎的波罗阻止你的话
..had there been no watchful Poirot to stop you.
将噩梦带走 告诉她 诺顿才是
Take the nightmare away and show how Norton, not her sister,
导致她父亲死亡的元凶 而不是她姐姐
was responsible for the death of her father.
黑斯廷斯上校
Captain Hastings?
我没有别的话要说了
I have no more to say.
我所做的事是正义的吗
Am I justified in what I have done?
我不知道
I do not know.
我不认为一个人应该将法律掌控于自己手中
I do not believe that a man should take the law into his own hands,
取了诺顿的性命 我是否也拯救了别的生命呢
but by taking the life of Norton, have I not saved others?
我一直以来都很相信自己 可这一次...
I have always been so sure, but now...
当那一刻来临的时候
When the moment comes,
我不会再救我自己
I will not try to save myself,
而是卑微虔诚地把灵魂交予上帝
but humbly offer my soul to God
祈求他的仁慈
and pray for his mercy.
一切都由他来定夺
It is for him to decide.
黑斯廷斯 我亲爱的朋友
Ah, Hastings, my dear friend,
过去的时光多么美好
they were good days.
是啊 过去的时光一直都那么美好
Yes, they have been good days.
赫尔克里・波罗
Hercule...Poirot.
T T